Guide to the Bob Nelkin Collection of ACC-PARC Records, 1953-2000 MSS 1002
Heinz History Center
- State School and Hospital (SSH) and Interim Care Committee Records, 1972-1997; II.
  - Polk Center, c1966-1997; 3.
    - Case Files and Notes, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - Placement of Michael W. Letter, January 12, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 29, Item 1)
        A letter from attorney Eric Anderson to Clay Appel inquiring about the feasibility of foster home placement for Michael W., an individual with intellectual and developmental disabilities. Anderson states that Michael W. has been in a shelter for six months waiting for placement in an institution or a group home. Anderson credits Bob Nelkin for giving him information about foster homes.
    - Case Files and Notes Regarding Death, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Memo Regarding Death of Carl Fisher, May 6, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 30, Item 1)
        An ACC-PARC memo from Doug Spencer to fellow ACC-PARC members regarding the death of Carl Fisher, a resident of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Incident Report for the Death of Carl Fisher, April 16, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 30, Item 2)
        An incident report filed for the disappearance and death of Carl Fisher, a resident of Polk State School and Hospital.
      - "Death Is Ruled Accidental" Article, April 18, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 30, Item 3)
        An article from The Derrick newspaper regarding the ruling of the death of Carl Fisher, a resident of Polk State School and Hospital, as an accident.
      - Letter to Joseph Colombatto from C. Richard Slater Regarding Carl Fisher, April 15, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 30, Item 4)
        A letter from C. Richard Slater, director of the Residential Program Department at the Department of Public Welfare, to Joseph J. Colombatto, superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital, regarding the death of Carl Fisher, a Polk resident.
    - Raymond H. Case File Records (Death), 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - Investigation of the Death of Raymond Helman Letter, October 24, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 31, Item 1)
        A letter from Edward Harris to ACC-PARC President Dr. Norman Mulgrave reporting on the investigation into the death of Raymond Helman, a Polk State School and Hospital resident. Newspapers received a copy of this report for publication.
      - "Inquest Ordered in Polk Death" Article, August 29, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 31, Item 2)
        An article from The News-Herald newspaper regarding the investigation into the death of Raymond Helman, a resident of Polk State School and Hospital.
    - Dispersal Task Force Records, 1973-1977 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - Notes on Polk Dispersal Meeting, December 27, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 32, Item 1)
        Notes taken, possibly by Bob Nelkin, during a meeting in Harrisburg regarding the Polk Dispersal Project.
      - Polk Dispersal Plan Outline, January 9, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 32, Item 2)
        A letter from Charles Peters to members of the Polk State School Dispersal Task Force outlining the plan to disperse up to one-third of the population at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - "Polk Improving, but Patient Load Problems Persist" Article, February 8, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 32, Item 3)
        An article from the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette about the new superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital Joseph Colombatto, improvements at Polk, and the issue of overcrowding still prevalent at the institution.
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Anna Belle Calloway, September 18, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 32, Item 4)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin, associate executive director of ACC-PARC, to Anna Belle Calloway, deputy secretary of the Department of Public Welfare's Western Region, requesting information on the Polk Dispersal Project and if the DPW plans to expand the project.
      - Letter from Charles Peters to Peter Polloni, May 12, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 32, Item 5)
        A letter from Charles Peters, administrator of the Allegheny County Mental Health/Mental Retardation/Drug and Alcohol Program, to Peter Polloni, deputy secretary of the Office of Mental Retardation in the Department of Public Welfare. Peters expresses his support for the Polk Dispersal Project and a transition to community living arrangements for Polk State School and Hospital residents. Peters also expresses concern over future issues such as Polk's geriatric population.
      - Community Living Arrangements Plan Fiscal Year 1977-1978, May 6, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 32, Item 6)
        An update to the Community Living Arrangements Plan for the fiscal year 1977-1978 as it relates to the Polk Dispersal Plan to disperse a portion of the population at Polk Center to alternative living arrangements.
    - Report: Facility Survey (Dispersal), 1973 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - News Clippings, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - News Clippings Regarding Cages, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - News Clippings Regarding Conditions, 1973-1997 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - News Clippings, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Nick D'Aluisio, July 15, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 38, Item 1)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin, associate executive director of ACC-PARC, to Nick D'Aluisio, assistant superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital, praising the institution for an updated manual for employees but disagrees with the use of restraints on residents.
      - Letter from Marlene Burda to Norman Taylor, December 9, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 38, Item 2)
        A letter from Marlene Burda, chairwoman on the PARC Residential Services Committee, to Norman Taylor, Deputy Secretary of the Western Region of the Department of Public Welfare, inquiring into the 110 electric beds promised to Polk State School and Hospital. Burda recently visited Polk and believes that the beds will improve the quality of life for residents.
    - Dispersal - Park Nursing Home Correspondence, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - Letter from Kenneth Winograd to Charles Peters, January 22, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 40, Item 1)
        A letter from Associate Administrator for Planning and Evaluation of the Allegheny County Mental Health and Mental Retardation Program, Kenneth Winograd, to Charles Peters, Commissioner of the Office of Mental Retardation's Western Region. Winograd is troubled by the possibility of the OMR scaling back the funding for day programs offered to Polk State School and Hospital residents living at Allegheny Valley School.
      - Letter from Charles Peters to Virginia Thornburgh, February 20, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 40, Item 2)
        A letter from Charles Peters, Commissioner of Mental Retardation for the Department of Public Welfare, to Virginia Thornburgh, president of ACC-PARC, regarding two court commitments to Polk State School.
      - Letter from Virginia Thornburgh to Norman Taylor, February 10, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 40, Item 3)
        A letter from Virginia Thornburgh, ACC-PARC president, to Norman Taylor, deputy secretary of the Department of Public Welfare, expressing frustration with new admissions accepted to Polk State School despite overcrowding and dispersal efforts.
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Joseph Colombatto, June 10, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 40, Item 4)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin, associate executive director of ACC-PARC, to Joseph Colombatto, superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital, asking about admissions to Polk in the past year. Nelkin hopes that Polk halts admissions like Western State School and Hospital.
    - Correspondence Regarding Deaths, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - Letter from Ronald Archer to Bob Nelkin and Doug Spencer, April 17, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 41, Item 1)
        An internal ACC-PARC letter from Ronald Archer to Bob Nelkin and Doug Spencer regarding the death of Carl Fisher at Polk State School and Hospital.
    - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 42)
      - Nicholas D'Aluisio Response to 1976 Visit to Polk State School and Hospital, March 12-24, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 42, Item 1)
        Letters from Herbert Wilkerson, information officer for the Allegheny County Mental Health and Mental Retardation Program, and Nicholas D'Aluisio, superintendent of Polk State School and Hospital regarding a recent visit from Allegheny County's Base Servicre Units.
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Anna Belle Calloway (2), May 27, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 42, Item 2)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin, associate executive director of ACC-PARC, to Anna Belle Calloway, deputy secretary of the Department of Public Welfare's Western Region, urging for the development of a plan to expand the Polk Dispersal Project.
    - Correspondence Regarding Dispersal Program, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Letter from Larry Jenkins on behalf of Anna Bell Calloway to Bob Nelkin, June 10, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 43, Item 1)
        A letter from Larry Jenkins, acting commissioner of mental retardation for the Department of Public Welfare, on behalf of Anna Belle Calloway to Bob Nelkin, associate executive director of ACC-PARC, regarding plans for the Polk Dispersal Project.
    - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - Letter from Nicholas D'Aluisio to Bob Nelkin, January 18, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 44, Item 1)
        A letter from Nicholas D'Aluisio, superintendent of Polk Center, to Bob Nelkin, associate executive director of ACC-PARC, responding to the reports of a hiring freeze at the institution.
      - Letter from Bob Nelkin to Nicholas D'Aluisio, January 13, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 44, Item 2)
        A letter from Bob Nelkin, associate executive director for ACC-PARC, to Nicholas D'Aluisio, superintendent of Polk Center, regarding reports of a hiring freeze at the institution.
  - State Schools and Hospitals (SSH) and Interim Care Facilities, 1972-1984; 4.
    This subseries is comprised of records such as correspondence, news clippings, and various reports that document the advocacy efforts of ACC-PARC on behalf of the intellectually disabled residents at other various care facilities in Western Pa. Facilities represented in this subseries include the Cresson and Ebensburg Centers, the Highland Park Center, the Mountaintop School, the Pleasant Manor, the Ridgeview Center, the Robinson Development Center, Selinsgrove State School and Hospital, and the Stillmeadow School. Worthy of note are those records pertaining to the Highland Park Center, which document efforts by ACC-PARC to expose and eradicate the maladaptive behavior programming at this facility. This treatment plan included the use of cattle prods and physical restraints on people with disabilities.
    - Visitation Team Reports - ACC-PARC and PARC Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - L. Steuart Brown Memo to PARC Chapter Presidents and Executives, August 6, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 1)
        A memo from PARC President L. Steuart Brown regarding the implementation of a PARC resolution asking county chapters to monitor state institutions in their areas.
      - ACC-PARC Press Release, April 19, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 2)
        A copy of ACC-PARC's press release defending PARC President Patricia Clapp against criticism over her role in helping to remove Superintendent Dr. McClelland from Polk State School.
      - Patricia Clapp Memo to PARC Chapter Presidents and Executives, April 23, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 3)
        A memo from Patricia Clapp, president of PARC, to Chapter Presidents and Executives regarding the situation at Polk State School that led to the removal of Dr. James McClelland as superintendent.
      - Polk State School and Hospital Visit Report (3), January 24, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 4)
        A report by Virginia Thornburgh and Bob Nelkin detailing the deplorable conditions at Polk State School during a visit to the institution.
      - Letter from Helene Wohlgemuth to Mr. and Mrs. Rosenblatt, May 7, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 5)
        A letter from Helene Wohlgemuth reassuring concerned parents of a Polk State School resident in the aftermath of Superintendent Dr. James McClelland's dismissal.
      - "Mail Censorship Charged at Polk" Article, February 27, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 6)
        A scan of the "Mail Censorship Charged at Polk" article from the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette discussing the mail censorship and telephone restrictions at Polk State School and Hospital.
      - Letter from Robert Hiltner to Charles Peters, March 7, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 7)
        A letter from Robert Hiltner, superintendent of Western State School and Hospital, to Charles Peters of ACC-PARC. Hiltner states that he recognizes ACC-PARC as a legitimate advocacy organization that he hopes to work with to create a better living condition for the residents of WSSH. Hiltner also outlines the procedures for announced and unannounced visits to the institution.
      - Report on Visit to Laurelton State School and Hospital, March 9, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 8)
        A report by Virginia Thornburgh following a visit to Laurelton State School and hospital with Marcella Ganoe, Mifflin County ARC President. Thornburgh outlines her findings and includes recommendations for the institution.
      - Letter from Eleanor Elkin to Commissioner Ed Goldman, February 22, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 9)
        A letter from Eleanor Elkin, chairwoman of the Residential Services Committee, to Commissioner of Mental Retardation Ed Goldman listing PARC members' concerns and recommendations regarding conditions at Hamburg State School and Hospital.
      - Notes on Cresson State School Fire, February 15, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 10)
        A scan of notes, possibly written by Bob Nelkin, detailing the facts of the fire at Cresson State School.
      - Additional Notes on Fire at Cresson State School, February 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 11)
        A scan of handwritten notes related to a fire at Cresson State School that killed at least two patients.
      - "Sprinklers Cited in Retarded Fire Deaths" Article, February 17, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 12)
        A copy of the "Sprinklers Cited in Retarded Fire Deaths" article in the Pittsburgh Press regarding ACC-PARC's investigation into the fire at Cresson State School.
      - ACC-PARC News Release (3), February 16, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 13)
        A press release by ACC-PARC providing details of the fire at Cresson State School earlier that month.
      - Irene Stacy Community Mental Health Center Dispersal Letter, May 3, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 14)
        A letter from Elizabeth Honse, a caseworker at the Irene Stacy Community Mental Health Center, informing parents of children older than twelve years old with developmental and intellectual disabilities that they must seek alternative placement for their child.
      - Bob Nelkin Memo (2), March 9, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 15)
        A memo from Bob Nelkin to the State School and Hospital and Interim Care Committee detailing the cost of institutionalizing patients from Allegheny County.
      - Bob Nelkin Memo (3), June 11, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 45, Item 16)
        A memo from Bob Nelkin to fellow ACC-PARC members listing the daily and annual costs of maintaining Polk, Cresson, Western State, and Ebensburg State Schools.
    - Ebensburg and Cresson Centers Dental Services Advocacy Records, 1975-1979 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Letter from PARC Officers to Aldo Colautti, January 8, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 46, Item 1)
        A letter from PARC officers to Secretary Aldo Colautti commending steps taken by the Department of Public Welfare to improve dental care at state institutions. The PARC officers also urge Colautti to allocate more sufficient funds for staff and equipment to further this goal.
      - Letter from Jay Reznik to Peter Polloni, November 14, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 46, Item 2)
        A letter from Dr. Jay Reznik to Peter Polloni, deputy secretary of the Office of Mental Retardation in the Department of Public Welfare, expressing frustration regarding the DPW's slow response to his review of dental services at state institutions.
      - Dental Review of Ebensburg Center, c. 1978 (Box 4, Folder 46, Item 3)
        A scan of Dr. Jay Reznik's review of dental services for residents at Ebensburg Center. Reznik concluded that the institution provided grossly inadequate dental care to its residents.
      - Dental Review of Ebensburg Center (2), January 23, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 46, Item 4)
        A copy of the January 23, 1979 review of dental services offered to residents of Ebensburg Center. Peter Polloni, deputy secretary of the Office of Mental Retardation in the Department of Public Welfare, requested a review of Ebensburg following Dr. Jay Reznik's report of the dental care at the institution.
      - Dr. Reznik Dental Review of Cresson Center, c. 1978 (Box 4, Folder 46, Item 5)
        A copy of Dr. Jay Reznik's evaluation of dental services offered to Cresson Center residents. This report includes Reznik's interaction with the staff dentist and an evaluation of the teeth of residents.
      - Department of Health Dental Review of Cresson Center, January 23, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 46, Item 6)
        A copy of the Pennsylvania Department of Health's review of dental services offered to Cresson Center residents. Peter Polloni, deputy secretary of the Office of Mental Retardation in the Department of Public Welfare, requested this review to verify Dr. Jay Reznik's evaluation of Cresson Center's dental services.
      - Dental Services Press Packet, January 8, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 46, Item 7)
        A packet distributed by Dr. Jay Reznik and PARC at a press conference after a lack of action by the Department of Public Welfare concerning the dental care of residents of state schools and hospitals. The packet includes minutes, reports, and correspondence regarding the dental health of residents and actions needed.
    - Ebensburg and Cresson Centers Dental Services Advocacy Records, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 47)
      - Dental Inventory Planned Strategy, February 9, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 47, Item 1)
        Correspondence between Peter Polloni, deputy secretary of the Office of Mental Retardation in the Department of Public Welfare, to Secretary Helene Wohlgemuth regarding proposed strategies to improve the dental health of residents of state schools and hospitals. A copy of the proposed dental service inventory plan from the Department of Public Welfare to improve the dental health of residents of state schools and hospitals accompanies this correspondence.
      - Letter from Alfredo Reyes to Donald Hartley, February 8, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 47, Item 2)
        A letter from Dr. Alfredo Reyes, medical director of Ebensburg Center, to Superintendent Donald Hartley expressing outrage regarding Dr. Jay Reznik's review of dental services offered to residents of the institution.
      - Ebensburg Center Dental Extractions Policy Bulletin, July 20, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 47, Item 3)
        A policy bulletin from Dr. Donald Hartley, superintendent of Ebensburg Center, explaining the procedure for emergency and non-emergency dental extractions for residents.
      - Letter from Helen O'Bannon to Teddi Leiden, February 6, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 47, Item 4)
        A letter from Helen O'Bannon to Teddi Leiden, president of PARC, regarding the dental reviews by Dr. Jay Reznik and the Department of Health. O'Bannon lists actions taken by the Department of Public Welfare in response to those reports.
      - Letter from Teddi Leiden to Aldo Colautti, January 16, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 47, Item 5)
        A letter from Teddi Leiden, president of PARC, to Aldo Colautti, secretary of the Department of Public Welfare, requesting copies of Dr. Jay Reznik's review of dental services at state schools and hospitals.
      - Proposed Plan for Dental Service Reviews, January 1979 (Box 4, Folder 47, Item 6)
        A proposed plan by the Department of Public Welfare for dental service reviews in response to Dr. Jay Reznik's reviews of Cresson Center and Ebensburg Center.
    - Cresson Center and Ebensburg Center News Clippings, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Ebensburg Center Correspondence, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 49)
      - Letter from Elsie Schmidt and Marlene Burda to Frank Beal, January 9, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 49, Item 1)
        A letter from Elise Schmidt, president of PARC, and Marlene Burda, chairwoman of the PARC Residential Services Committee, to Secretary Frank Beal of the Department of Public Welfare. Schmidt and Burda report to Beal the conditions of Ebensburg Center following a visit to the institution.
      - Letter from Marlene Burda to Harry Herman, January 9, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 49, Item 2)
        A letter from Marlene Burda, chairwoman of the PARC Residential Services Committee, to Harry Herman, superintendent of Ebensburg Center, regarding PARC's findings during an unannounced visit to the institution and the participation by Herman and his staff.
      - Narrative Report of Ebensburg Center, January 9, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 49, Item 3)
        The narrative report of an unannounced visit to Ebensburg Center by Marlene Burda, chairwoman of the PARC Residential Services Committee, and PARC Region IV Vice-President Teddi Leiden. PARC visited Buildings 3, 4, and 6 observing and commenting on physical surroundings, food service, clothing, resident appearance, programming, medical care, staff attitude, and rights of residents. This report accompanied a letter to Harry Herman, superintendent of Ebensburg Center, from Burda.
      - Letter to Charles Inlander, November 7, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 49, Item 4)
        An anonymous letter to Charles Inlander regarding a lack of programming at a recent visit to a state school, including a lack of educational programming for many of the school-aged residents.
      - PARC Residential Services Committee Report Format, c. 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 49, Item 5)
        A copy of the PARC Residential Services Committee's standard report format for visits to residential facilities.
      - Letter to Charles Inlander (2), 1975-12-04 (Box 4, Folder 49, Item 6)
        An unsigned letter to Charles Inlander regarding the author's visit to Ebensburg Center and the lack of educational programming available for residents.
    - Ebensburg Center Report: PARC, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - Narrative Report of Ebensburg Center Draft, October 7, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 50, Item 1)
        A draft of the narrative report for a visit to Ebensburg Center by ACC-PARC and PARC members. Members visited Buildings 3, 4, and 6 observing and commenting on physical surroundings, food service, clothing, resident appearance, programming, medical care, staff attitude, and rights of residents.
    - Highland Park Center Rights of the Intellectually Disabled, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - Highland Park Center Policies, March 17, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 51, Item 1)
        A copy of policies at Highland Park Center that aligns with the United Nation's 1971 Declaration on the Rights of Mentally Retarded Persons and a copy of Highland Park Center's 1976 edition of the Bill of Rights for residents.
    - Highland Park Center Residents Rights, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - Highland Park Center Statement of Resident's Rights, December 1979 (Box 4, Folder 52, Item 1)
        Highland Park Center's Statement of Resident's Rights. Sections of this statement include communications, free exercise of religion, labor, money and possessions, least restrictive setting, treatment, redress of grievances, abuse, voting, visitation by outside groups, discipline, and restraints.
    - Highland Park Center Maladaptive Behavior Programming Correspondence, Reports, and Policies, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Letter from N. Karen Kelly to Walter Cohen, June 2, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 53, Item 1)